YWCA of the U.S.A. Records. Record Group 6. Program: Series IV. Constituent Groups
Sophia Smith Collection
1945-46 "Constituency" under Community Division, staff member added for Agricultural
1947-49 Headquarters-based Staff under Community Division
1950 Young Adult under Community Division
Scope and Content
Employed Women Program records include general and history files; committee and department minutes and reports; extensive conference files; National and Regional Council records; organizations files; programs and projects files; publications; reference materials; studies; and training materials.
Most of the records in this series are those gathered in the National Association's Central File, and date primarily from the post World War I staff reorganization and the establishment of the National Assemblies (1922-24) up to 1950. Earlier materials (primarily Industrial) can be found in Method Department records in Series I of this Record Group. Few records date from after 1950 when the working women's Councils were combined with other groups into the Young Adult Council. There are a few files on the Business Office Culture Project and Job-Corps YWCA Extension Residence Programs of the 1960s and 70s, and scattered items from the 1980s. [see also Subseries E. Young Adults]
Because the working women's clubs and councils were self-governing groups, the records associated with their activities, including the conferences they planned, were often written by the working women themselves. While some of the documents are reports by National Staff on attendance at conferences or council meetings, much is in the voice of the working women members.
The extensive Conference files can include: planning materials such as local arrangements files, mailings, and pre-conference study materials; items for use during the conference such as programs, schedules, handouts, training materials, daily meditations, skit scripts, song sheets, and bulletins with drawings and other art work, poetry and fiction by conference participants; and summary materials such as reports, participants lists, financial records, training materials, and evaluations.
The Household Employment files were compiled for the YWCA's Central Subject File and include various records of various committees and commissions working on related issues, as well as local associations files with correspondence, reports, surveys, and reference materials on household employment issues and training programs (not necessarily YW programs) in various regions of the country.
Microfilmed Records, 1906-70 only
[see Microfilmed Records Reel List]
Most of the records on the microfilm were retained in original format. The one category of records that is probably more complete in original format is publications. Records of program related to Employed Women can be found on the microfilm under:
Minutes and Reports
B. and P. [Business and Professional] Committee
B.P. and I. [Business, Professional, and Industrial]
Co-operating Committee, Central Club for Nurses
Industrial Committee
Young Adult Council
Subject Files
Business and Industrial Women
Business and Professional Women
Business, Professional and Industrial Women
Economics
Household Employment [Domestic Service]
Industrial
Job Corps-J.C.Y.W.
Labor
Original Format Records, 1870-84, n.d., 24.5 linear feet
[see Original Format Records folder list]
Most of the records that were microfilmed were retained in original format. The one category of records that is probably more complete in original format is publications.
Materials about the YWCA's work with employed women is in sections as follows:
General contains records of combined B and P, Industrial, and Agricultural activities, committees, conferences, and councils. There are also files on early (1906-19) general working women's groups, general employment-related publications and studies, and general work-related projects from the 1960s and 70s (including the Job-Corps YWCA Extension Residence Program). Records of YWCA research projects, publications, and activities related to Unemployment during the 1920s and 1930s are filed at the end of this section.
Business and Professional Women contains general historical materials, committee minutes, extensive summer and weekend conference records, National and Area Council and National Assembly records, files on work with related organizations, a few files on the Business Office Culture Project of the late-1960s, publications, and studies.
Household Employment contains general historical materials, committee and commission records, Local Associations files; records of Industrial Assembly and Conference Household Employment Project, files on cooperating organizations, publications, and reference materials.
Industrial Work contains general historical materials, including some files on local Industrial Clubs and Committees, Committee records, extensive Summer and Weekend/Mid-winter Conference files, National and Area Council records; files on National Assemblies, program and project files, publications, reports, studies, and training materials.
Related Materials
In other Subseries in this Series:
Subseries D. Teen Age and Younger Girls Program contains studies of younger employed girls and program materials created for them, plus additional Younger Girls in Business and Industry (YGBI) Clubs. There are also records of some employment training programs and projects developed specifically for teenagers, such as the Young Women's Employment Project (1980s), and the Youth Workers Team Learning Project (1970s).
Subseries E. Young Adults has records of the consolidated programs for YW-Wives, younger employed women, Students, and Teen-Agers dating from 1950 to 1979.
In other Series in this Record Group:
SERIES III. PUBLIC ADVOCACY contains records of the YWCA's involvement with labor legislation and other workers' issues.
SERIES VII. WAR WORK AND DEFENSE SERVICES contains records of the YWCA's work on behalf of women mobilized into Industry in both World Wars.
In other Record Groups:
Records of the two predecessor organizations document their work on behalf of employed women are in RECORD GROUP 2. PREDECESSOR ORGANIZATIONS AND NATIONAL BOARD.
RECORD GROUP 4. NATIONAL CONVENTIONS AND CONFERENCES has small files on Industrial and B and P Assemblies convened at Conventions and documentation of resolutions and actions related to employed women's issues.
RECORD GROUP 7. STUDENT WORK: The Student Department formed clubs and developed summer Student-Industrial Programs in the 1920s and 30s to bring together college students and working women for joint study and Christian fellowship.
RECORD GROUP 8. COMMUNITY ASSOCIATIONS: The earliest discussions of the new National Association's work with employed women are recorded in the records of the Association Extension Committee. Other materials can be found in the records of the Rural Communities Department, Mill Villages work and rural-industrial studies, and Employment and Room Registry reports on local conditions. Microfilmed Local Associations files contain records of interactions between National Staff and Industrial Branches and some studies of local industrial conditions. They also contain records of the national organization's interaction with Mill Village YWCAs.
RECORD GROUP 8. COMMUNITY ASSOCIATIONS The Local Associations files on the microfilm have records of National Association contacts with "Industrial" branches in some cities.
There are many photographs of women working and of Employed women's conferences in RECORD GROUP 9. PHOTOGRAPHS, ARTIFACTS, AND RECORD GROUP 10. AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS.
In Personal Papers:
The Lillian Sharpley Papers contain notes and drafts for a history of the YWCA's work with Business and Professional women.
The Grace Dodge Papers contain a scrapbook of writings with many articles about household employment.
SUBSERIES B. IMMIGRATION AND FOREIGN COMMUNITIES Historical Note
One of the tasks of the staff of the newly established YWCA of the U.S.A. was to decide what kinds of work the National Association should do; which existing YWCA activities it should try to coordinate at the national level and what new types of work it should attempt. Examination of these issues was the charge of the Extension and Sociological Investigation Committee (later the Association Extension Committee) which had its first meeting late in 1907. It seems to have been a given that City, Student, and Foreign work would continue under the new National Association, but all other types of "extension" of the work were first studied by the Committee.
At its first meeting in 1907 the Extension and Sociological Investigation Committee of the new National Association considered, among other things, whether or how the National Association should serve young immigrant women. At issue were "the difficulty of other religious organizations working there, owing to the almost complete control of the field by the Catholic church" and "the seeming necessity for settlement work, since there are so many men, women and children in need, young women being in the minority." Given these complications, the Committee resolved to study the matter further. Over its first year they received suggestions from various organizations about specific ways the YWCA might serve young immigrant women, such as meeting them upon arrival, assisting them to their destination, and aiding them in finding employment. Another area of concern was "the Americanization and Christianization of immigrant girls working in American homes."
YWCA of the USA president Grace Dodge appointed a Special Committee of Research and Investigation in April 1910 in response to "recent revelations of the adverse conditions surrounding Immigrant women and girls as they come to America" which made it "imperative that the [YWCA]... should at least study the question to see if there is a need which it can meet, which is not being met by any other organization." After a summer of study in New York City, the National Association inaugurated a demonstration program for young immigrant women in the fall of 1910 under the auspices of the Association Extension Committee.
The National Association engaged Edith Terry [later Bremer] to establish what eventually became the International Institute of the City of New York. The Institute initially offered English classes and staff wrote and published materials for adults learning the language. Members of the Special Committee visited Community Associations outside of New York to consult and coordinate their fledgling immigrant programs.
The National Association's work with foreign-born women aimed to "serve the Association and the entire American community by bringing into association women of many nationalities, widening the acquaintance and increasing the understanding of all, and developing internationalism by training in internationality friendships." It was also designed to serve "the immigrant woman by helping her to a 'more abundant life'... helping her and her American-born daughter to understand and appreciate each other," and to make the U.S. known and loved by its new citizens. The specifics of the program were tailored to the interests and needs of the constituents, but the basic idea was essentially the same as elsewhere in the Association.
In addition to English classes, the Association program for young immigrant women came to include "wholesome recreation," technical classes to raise their "economic value," practical and scientific instruction for home life or domestic service (for those wishing it), understanding of American standards and ideals, and "character" instruction.
National Staff facilitated the establishment of special branches of Community YWCAs to serve non-English speaking young women wherever the size of a city's immigrant population warranted it. The National Association decided to call these branches International Institutes, once it learned that the word "Association" had negative (commercial or radical) connotations for Europeans. By contrast "Institutes" were associated with "protection obtained and something learned."
National work on behalf of immigrant women also included work fostering understanding and appreciation of their cultures among the total membership and the general public. In addition to texts for teaching English as a second language, National staff for "Immigration and Foreign Communities" work produced "technical" materials about cultures, languages, history, and customs, and corresponded with Community Associations and various other organizations about "relating to foreign people." An adaptation of the Eight Week Club Plan, called International Friendship Clubs, matched college YWCA women home for the summer with high school girls in small towns. Program staff developing ideas for recreational activities incorporated research by the Foreign Communities staff into song books, programs for folk festivals, and suggestions for programs, pageants, and plays. The National Association encouraged celebration of the richness these cultures brought to the U.S. and to the Association. YWCA serials consistently included articles, and Conferences regularly incorporated some kind of program, designed to foster appreciation in the general membership of immigrant issues and cultures.
World War I precipitated a significant increase in both the size and complexity of the national program of "Work with Foreign-Born Women." In her first report for the fall of 1917, Edith Terry Bremer noted that "The American idea about immigrants has completely changed." The War suddenly made "every foreign home a place of dread and fear and suspicion." "It is queer and inconsistent," she wrote in her October 17, 1917 report, "that the same situation that has melted the hearts of Americans toward Europeans in Europe has hardened and made exacting and suspicious those same hearts toward Europeans in America!!!"
In its capacity as a member of the National War Work Council, the YWCA assumed responsibility for the care and protection of women as they were affected by the war. Noting that the effects of the war were even more severe for foreign-born women, the YWCA ramped up its efforts on their behalf. It essentially nationalized what had been a northeastern U.S. operation. With War Work Council funding, multi-lingual secretaries were hired for Port Work, meeting immigrant women at points of intake on the east and west coasts; staff of a new International Information and Service Bureau translated all kinds of technical materials and wrote speeches and information sheets in a variety of languages "upon all matters for which they are needing help;" other secretaries did Emergency Field work to help speed the opening of new International Institutes for young women of all nationalities; a Bureau was established to help in locating refugee relatives in Europe; and the YWCA provided "home service" for the families of enlisted men. To facilitate all this new work and reconstruction work in Europe, the YWCA established training programs for foreign community workers and reconstruction volunteers. Most of the "Foreign Communities" staff worked under the auspices of the War Work Council from the fall of 1917 through the post-war Continuation period. With the nationalization of the efforts, the staff began to serve immigrant populations different from the primarily European groups prevalent in the northeast and Midwest, particularly Mexican immigrants in the southwest and Asian immigrants on the west coast.
Once the Continuation funds were exhausted, the National Association was forced to make drastic cuts to its Foreign Communities staff. Many of the War Work staff found work in the new International Institutes supported by Community YWCAs. With the advent of the Great Depression it became difficult to maintain even a reduced level of services and the Association sought ways to simplify its program. Noting that immigration work was most effective when it included all family members, not just its young women, the National Association and other agencies working on behalf of the foreign born facilitated the creation of a new national organization to oversee the work. The National Institute of Immigrant Welfare, established in 1934, assumed much of the program the YWCA had developed, including administration of the International Institutes. The NIIW named the YWCA's longtime director of Immigration and Foreign Communities Work, Edith Terry Bremer, its first executive director.
From that time National YWCA work related to immigration and immigrants was more-or-less confined to public advocacy. [See SERIES III. PUBLIC ADVOCACY] During World War II, the National Association once again established similar (though more small-scale) services for aiding war refugees. It also ran programs for Japanese-Americans sent to Relocation Centers. [See SERIES VII. WAR WORK AND DEFENSE SERVICES.]
With the exception of African-Americans, the role of racial and ethnic groups in the National Association is largely undocumented between 1934 and the 1970 "One Imperative" Convention and its associated Institutes, Workshops, and Consultations.
That Convention prompted the National Association to broaden its idea about racism to include other racial and ethnic groups in a new "Racial Justice" program. [see Subseries C. Interracial/Racial Justice below]
Administrative History
Oct 1910 Special Worker, Immigration Work for the Association Extension Committee
1911 Department of Method
1912 Immigration Work, City Department in the Department of Method
1916 "Immigration and Foreign Community Work" in the Department of Method
Sep 1918 Special Workers at Headquarters, Foreign-born Women, War Work Staff and Department of Method
Dec 1918 Work for Foreign-Born Women, War Work Staff
Jan 1920 Work for Foreign-Born Women, Continuation Committee staff
1921 Post-Continuation Committee staff
1923 Dept for Work with Foreign-Born Women under Field Division
1925 Dept for Immigration and Foreign Communities under Field Division
1932 International Institutes and Foreign Communities, Studies and Program Materials under Laboratory Division; and International Institutes and Foreign Communities under National Services Division
1933 Bureau of Immigration and the Foreign-Born
fall 1935 Nationality Community Interests in Program and Research under Laboratory Division
1936 International Interests (or Nationality Community Interests) in Program, and Research under Laboratory Division
1939 Refugees in Program and Research under Laboratory Division
1940-43 Nationality Community Interests in Community Division
1944 Committee on Refugees secretary in General Administration and Japanese Evacuees (special project)
Scope and Content
Records of the National Immigration and Foreign Communities work includes general historical materials, correspondence, minutes, conference files, records of cooperation with other organizations working on immigration and refugee issues, publications, reference files, reports, studies, and training materials.
The Original Format Records include significant un-microfilmed materials from Elizabeth Hendee, head of the Vocational Guidance Bureau.
Microfilmed Records, 1910-70 only
[see Microfilmed Records Reel List]
The Minutes and Reports and much of the Immigration section of the Subject File were not discarded after microfilming, so many of the microfilmed materials can also be consulted in original format.
Local Associations files include records of the national office's interactions with various International Institutes. They can be found on the film following the general files for a local association. (For example, under Missouri, general files about the Saint Louis Association appear on reel 187 at microdex 2, these are followed by "Saint Louis--Carondelet Branch," which is followed by "Saint Louis-International Institute.") These materials were discarded after microfilming, so are only available on the microfilm.
Immigration and Foreign Communities materials can be found on the microfilm under:
Minutes and Reports
Immigration and Foreign Communities Committee
Research and Investigation Committee
Subject Files
Immigration
Immigration-International Institutes
Local Association files
International Institute - filed alphabetically by state and then by City of name of the Association
Original Format Records, 1911-93, 4.5 linear feet
[see Original Format Records Folder List]
Beyond the microfilmed Subject File and Minutes and Reports, the original format records contain additional publications, articles and theses about the work, and some of Elizabeth Hendee's Vocational Guidance Bureau office working files received by the National Board Archives long after the records were microfilmed. These files were incorporated into the original format records described below.
The Original format records are arranged as follows:
General and History contains general historical materials including brochures and pamphlets.
Department, Committees, and Commissions contains minutes of the major committees, and some staff meetings; records of the Commission on the Study of the Second Generation Girl, a group studying the challenges faced by the children of new immigrants, 1925-35; department correspondence and mailings called "Program Letters"; records related to process by which the National Association facilitated founding of the National Institute of Immigrant Welfare; general information on International Institutes and their policies; a small group of autobiographies by International Institute members; and some records of the Vocational Guidance Bureau.
Conferences contains records of national conferences of International Institutes and foreign communities YWCA staff, 1917-45.
Organizations has records of interactions with the National Institute of Immigrant Welfare including some committee files and publications dating from its founding in 1934 to 1949. There are also files of correspondence with civil liberties, refugee welfare, and citizenship education organizations from the World War II era.
Publications includes technical bulletins and handbooks for understanding and working with foreign-born members; tools for teaching English as a second language; books about folk festivals, ethnic costumes, and some International Institute cookbooks. There are also several serial publications including Foreign Born, published by the National Association, 1919-22.
Reference files includes bibliographies and subject files compiled by the staff on such topics as race and nationality, displaced persons, "mother tongue," and "background materials" on countries.
Reports includes Department, Committee and Commission, International Institute, secretary and visitation reports, 1910-42.
Studies are on various topics from the 1920s and 30s.
Training materials are primarily related to training staff to work with foreign community members (1918-35) and include some general information about the summer training program at Fletcher Farm in Ludlow, Vermont.
Related Materials
In other Subseries in this Series:
Subseries D. Teenage and Younger Girls: information about other cultures and the lives of foreign-born girls were a regular feature in materials for Teen conferences and in the Teen serial The Bookshelf.
In other Series in this Record Group:
SERIES I. DEPARTMENT, STAFF AND COMMITTEES: Immigration and Foreign Communities staff reported to the Association Extension Committee and then the Research and Method Department up to World War I. Discussions of the work and additional secretary's reports can be found there.
SERIES III. PUBLIC ADVOCACY: Beginning with World War I, the National Program for Public Advocacy included a variety of efforts on behalf of refugees, immigration legislation, and other related topics. After World War II, Public Advocacy is pretty much the only way the National Association is involved in immigrant issues.